Mariano Riva Palacio Collection:
University of Texas at Austin
- Enero-Junio 1850
  - 3838 Flores Pensado, Ignacio. Mexico, February 11, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 22 × 28 cm.
    Request for letter of recommendation for French resident, Eugenio Maillefert, traveling to the United States in an effort to organize and construct a railroad from Mexico to Puebla; intervention with Luis de la Rosa.
  - 3839 Alas, M. Arcos, February 11, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Departure of convoy; insecurity of the roads; suspicion of soldiers; León; articles in El Progreso criticizing the government and mining industry; Sámano; opposition to Calderón; fear of bandits.
  - 3840 Riva Palacio, Mariano. [Borrador de carta.] February 12, 1850. Unsigned., 2 l. 13 × 20 cm., 1 l. 16 × 22 cm., 1 l. 13 × 16 cm.
    Critical situation of the treasury; proposed Ley de capitación; impatience with incompetent officials; request for aid in popularizing law.
  - 3841 Álvarez, Juan. Iguala, February 12, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Receipt of letter through Lic. Trinidad Gómez; Gavilán; letter to the Ministerio de Relaciones on railroads; Cantú; Haro; Aburto.
  - 3842 Villanueva, Zenón. [Carta a Agustín Díaz.] Tecamac, February 12, 1850. LS., 2 l. 22 × 26 cm.
    Pack train sent under Patricio Flores to move furniture; advice on dealing with the Ayuntamiento.
  - 3843 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, February 12, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for advice on house, No. 1 Ángel; stalemate between puros, Conservadores, and Santanistas; support of Suárez Iriarte; police established in Cuajimalpa under José María Ortega; Zumingo (Zeuncingo); difficulties of MacKintosh; trial of Perdigón as robber.
  - 3844 García, José María. Valle, February 13, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for cureñas for the cannon furnished the Guardia nacional; Arizcorreta; visitors to Temascaltepec; disorder in Municipalidad de Otzoloapam; absence of León; partiality of prefect toward Alvarado and his terrorists; opposition to control of Guardia nacional by local Ayuntamiento and subprefect.
  - 3845 Segura, Sebastián. Mexico, February 13, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Legislative proposal of Diputado Joaquín Navarro for 3% tax on silver to be raised to 4% and to become revenue of the Federal Government; derecho de fortificación de muralla in Veracruz made Federal revenue; absence of Bandera from post in Oficina de contribuciones; Legislature to close in April; return to duties in Pachuca; dieta.
  - 3846 Cruz, Agustín. Cuernavaca, February 14, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Interviews with Cano, Gutiérrez, Orellana, and Aparicio; Yáñez' reports of increased tax payments; claims for debts due to Anglo-American occupation; absence of Silva in Dolores; payments due Silva and Cajida; Romero requested to join rurales de Quevedo in pursuit of robbers and counterfeiters near Chalma; Martínez, Villegas.
  - 3847 Vecinos de Yautepec. [Petición a Jesús Navarro.] Yautepec, February 15, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Order of Supremo Tribunal for investigation by the Juez de Tetecala; accusations by Ganancia; assurance of tranquility in the town. Signed by Manuel Abascal, Apolinario Roxa, Guadalupe López, Mariano Gómez, Antonio Barba, Cruz Cedano, Tiburcio Torres (Ferres?), Juan Marín, and Marciano López Moctezuma.
  - 3848 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, February 15, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Promise to work for acceptance of the Ley de capitación; circular for parish priests; complaints of conscripts minimized; prostitution; Alas; political conditions in Municipalidad de Otzoloapam and in Villa del Valle.
  - 3849 P[érez] Palacios, Luis. Hacienda de Apanq[]co (?), February 15, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Assurance of public order in Yautepec.
  - 3850 Ortiz Monasterio, José María. Mexico, February 15, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 30 cm.
    Transmittal of request of the Promotor fiscal interino (Covarrubias), Mexico, February 4, 1850, for deposition from Riva Palacio concerning responsibility of Pedro Fernández del Castillo, Ministro Tesorero, for payment of bonds held by Manning and MacKintosh; Segundo Juez suplente Lic. Bernardo Guimbarda; Escandón; Tribunal del Circuito de México.
  - 3851 Lezama, Juan. Tulancingo, February 16, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Meeting of officials to discuss the Ley de capitación; problems of collecting the tax; empadronamiento; poverty of indentured workers; opposition to surrender of tax collection to private individuals; budget estimates printed in El Porvenir; leyes de contribuciones.
  - 3852 Riva Palacio, Vicente. Mexico, February 16, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Impossibility of doubling-up on second and third years in college.
  - 3853 Sáenz de Sicilia, José I. Apam, February 16, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Inefficient tax collection in past; collection by personal contact; padrón; support of the Ley de capitación; Municipalidad de Tepeapulco; pulque manufacture; payment by Benito Macua; Recaudación de Calpulalpan; $800 paid by writer; Gabino Sánchez.
  - 3854 [Riva Palacio, Mariano.] [Borradores.] Toluca, February 17, 1850. Unsigned., 3 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    - a. [Borrador de carta a Luis Cuevas.] f. 1. Quarrel between manufacturers and hacendados over distribution of water; arrangements for a meeting of all involved on both sides; letter to Garay.
    - b. [Borrador de carta a Antonio Garay.] 1 l. f. 2-2v. Dispute between hacendados and manufacturers in Partido de Tlalpam: Fábricas de la Magdalena; water rights; trip to Coyoacán requested to obtain order for meeting of all litigants.
    - c. [Borrador de carta a José del Villar.] 1 l. f. 3. Provision for meeting of litigants over water rights.
  - 3854A Andrade, Cristóbal. Huejutla, February 18, 1850. LS., 1 l. 23 × 27 cm.
    Reports of rebellion in Ciudad Victoria; reëlection of Governor Jesús Cárdenas; public order in Huasteca and along borders of States of Mexico, Puebla, Veracruz, and San Luis.
  - 3855 De la Trouplinière, C. Cuautitlán, February 18, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Orders given the cuadrillas for care of the roads; return to Toluca.
  - 3856 Alcocer, Luis A. Tenanz[]o, February 18, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Regret over attacks on Riva Palacio in the press. Note on back; Asuntos de Tornel y Quintana.
  - 3857 Iturbe, Francisco. Mexico, February 18, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Tax-payers' fear of Oliveros; experience in Morelia with the Ley de capitación; fiscal condition of Puebla State; memoria published by the governor; pay of deputies; article on colonization in Veracruz newspaper; Zurutuza criticized for bringing mountain workers to Arroyozarco; liberal institutions urged; answer to criticism through the Periódico oficial suggested; hacendados and the land problem; contracts for toll roads; spending of the indemnity; criticism of Nuevo León law taxing merchants from other states; hostilities feared between Chiapas and Tabasco; troubles of the Governor of Tamaulipas; improper balance between taxes and deputies; rising hopes of the conservatives.
  - 3858 Salazar, Agustín. Ixtlahuaca, February 18, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Promise of continued support.
  - 3859 Olmedo, Manuel de. February 18, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Problems of the Ley de capitación; local conditions hindering collection; appointment of commissioners with approval of the Ayuntamiento; formation of Padrones; Recaudadores de Zinacantepec and Lerma.
  - 3860 León, Estevan V. Tem[]c, February 19, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recruitment with Lieutenant Toribio Guerra; payment of troops by Rentas del Tabaco and Administradores de Sultepec and Zacualpam; local loans made by order of General Álvarez during Anglo-american occupation; approval of the Ley de capitación; banditry on road to Cerrogordo; criticism in El Progreso.
  - 3861 Riva Palacio, Mariano. [Borrador de carta al Ministro del despacho de relaciones.] February 20, 1850. Unsigned., 1 l. 21 × 28 cm.
    Answer to No. 3850. Discussion with Pedro Fernández del Castillo on payments to MacKintosh.
  - 3862 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, February 20, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Factories fined for depriving hacendados of water; criminals caught at Santa Fé sentenced; delay in sentence of Perdigón; Ley de capitación; formation of padrones.
  - 3863 Bassoco, José M. de. Mexico, February 20, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Advice on collection of the capitation tax.
  - 3864 Zerecero, A. Supremo Tribunal de Guerra y Marina, Mexico, February 20, 1850. ALS. 1 l. 15 × 21 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Recommendation for bearer as road guard between Toluca and Mexico.
  - 3865 Velázquez, J. Francisco. Guadalupe, February 20, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Defense of Oliveros; execution of Chávez of Juchi and a prisoner from Totolapa; executions by Comandante de Policía de Ameca; Puebla-Mexico stagecoach robbed; inquiries from Jueces de Letras de Puebla; Tomás Vargas released by Juez Letrado de Chalco.
  - 3866 Zurutuza, A[nselmo]. Mexico, February 20, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Protest against increase in toll for stagecoach along road to Cuautitlán; provisions of the law of 1843; advice of Arrangoiz; new toll policy set by Juan Becerril; responsibility of Riva Palacio for Mexico State and General Álvarez for State of Guerrero; road to Cuernavaca; need for road repairs.
  - 3867 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, February 20, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm., 1 l. 21 × 28 cm.
    Taxes on haciendas and brandy factories; debts incurred during the military occupation; news sent from Ventura Orellana to Agustín Cruz. Includes draft of answer, describing the duties of Agustín Cruz; transmittal of list of claimants; receipt of weapons for Guardia nacional.
  - 3868 Quintana Roo, Andrés. Mexico, February 21, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Delivery of letter from the Juez de Apam; illness with chest affliction; uprising in Apam incited by clérigo Mariano Mendoza; Juez de Letras Cortés; federal aid recommended.
  - 3869 Navarro, Juan R. Mexico, February 21, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Transmittal of new newspaper El Oriente, editor Juan Miguel de Lozada; subscription solicited.
  - 3870 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, February 21, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Defense of Oliveros from outside officials; Chalco; opposition to gambling by officials; family to be moved from Mexico to Texcoco; cholera in Mexico.
  - 3871 Terreros, Manuel. Mexico, February 21, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Absenteeism among deputies; alcabala proposed; band of outlaws planning to assault Jalpa; Noriega; power of attorney given Juan José Baz by Francisco Pérez, executed by Oliveros; charge against Oliveros; Escudero.
  - 3872 Buchan, Juan H. [Carta a Escandón.] Mineral del Monte, February 23, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm., 1 l. 21 × 31 cm.
    Report of illness; election of deputies presided over by the Prefect; Pachuca; to be diputado: Ignacio Castelazo of the Casa de Regla; Diputado Antonio Montiel, nominated by Joaquín Rosas of Mina de Manzano; substitutes: José Hidalgo of Minas de San Pedro y San Pablo and Resquiciote; Joaquín Bars, representative of Cortazar family; Francisco Verguiñan, miner from Zacualtipán; criticism of Pachuca; el Chico. Includes list of participants. Lista de los Señores mineros inscriptos en la nueva matricula pa. la elección de la diputación territorial del Mineral del Monte, cuya calificación se ha hecho en la Junta General verificada con tal objeto hoy dia de la fecha. Lists Miners (La Casa de Regla and La Compañía inglesa aviadora) Juan Buchan, Juan Callejas, Antonio Celís, Manuel Cortazar, Doña Ignacia Cuéllar de Cortazar (Testamentaría de José R. Castelazo). Rafael García. Joaquín González, Francisco Hernández, Doña Ignacia Hernández, Doña Manuela Hernández de Moral, Luis Herrera, Felipe Hidalgo, Juan C. Hidalgo, José Islas, José Lira, José Manzano, José María Martiarena, Ignacio Ortuño, Miguel Osorio, José Pérez, Santiago Ramírez, Joaquín Rosas, Gregorio Sagredo, Mariano Sánchez, Doña Juliana de la Torre, Doña Gertrudis Valencia, Doña Josefa Valencia, and Doña Vicenta Valencia; Rescatadores Isidro Butrón, Clemente Carmona, Juan Gansa, Hipólito Gutiérrez, Santiago Leyva, Juan N. Manzano, Sixto Mejía, Valentín Mejía; new miners Juan B. Castelazo, Damián Floresi, Agustín Limón, José Murphi, Tomás Murphi, Agustín Osorio, Julián Osorio, Luis Osorio, Teodoro Sagredo, Antonio Téllez, Guillermo Verguiñan, Pantaleón Villagrán, Mineral del Monte, Febrero 17 de 1850.
  - 3873 Álvarez, Juan. Iguala, February 23, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Custody of road between the two states; work on the ley orgánica; opposition of Aburto; disappointment over provisions strengthening power of the prefectos; plans to retire; praise for Cantú.
  - 3874 Payno, M[anuel]. Mexico, February 23, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Cumplido's defense of Riva Palacio in El Siglo; request for critical articles for study and answer; Revilla; Hermano Pepe; work on Comisión de Hacienda and Comisión de crédito público.
  - 3875 Martínez, Primitivo. Chalco, February 24, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Spread of cólera asiática in States of Zacatecas, Michoacán, and Guadalajara; antidote prepared by Dr. Mehars of Potosí compared with smallpox vaccination in importance; epidemic compared to that of 1833; failures in preparing the drug from chemical analysis; lack of funds for purchase of drugs; request for intervention with friends in Potosí to have Dr. Mehars come to State of Mexico.
  - 3876 Riva Palacio, Mariano. [Borrador de carta a José María Tornel.] Toluca, February 25, 1850. Unsigned., 1 l. 15 × 21 cm.
    Search for titles to Hacienda de San Juan de Dios; letter to the Juez de Chalco.
  - 3877 Zurutuza, A[nselmo]. Mexico, February 25, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Appeal to the Congreso del Estado concerning toll on the Cuautitlán road; Arrangoiz; repairs on Cuernavaca road to be halted by Juan Becerril.
  - 3878 Riva Palacio, Mariano. [Borrador de carta a Luis A. Alcocer.] Toluca, February 25, 1850. Unsigned. 2 l. 21 × 26 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Criticism of newspaper articles; general statement of political policy; construction in stone from Zumpaluca.
  - 3879 Zamudio, Luis. Mexico, February 25, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for back pay due from services with the rurales; partial payment by Olaguíbel; order for payment by Arizcorreta; archives in Sultepec; Agustín Cárdenas.
  - 3880 Navarro, Mariano. Jilotepe, February 25, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recovery from illness; settlement of litigation by citizens of San Lucas Detidí (?); contribution to Hospital de San Juan de Dios; sale of Rancho de Tecoloapan for construction of prison.
  - 3881 Sierra, Manuel María de la. Chalco, February 26, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Benito Acosta; opening of canal; dispute between Chalco and Tlahuac over tax privileges; comparison with administration of roads; delivery of Rojas by Oliveros delayed.
  - 3882 Escandón, Manuel. Mexico, February 26, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Convalescence in Tacubaya; approval of the Ley de capitación; opposition caused by economies in government; complaints against the contract for tobacco income; benefit of the contract system; contribution to jail construction; visit to Real del Monte urged; construction of fort; road to Pachuca.
  - 3883 Moreno, José Andrés. Huichapan, February 26, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Resignation as Administrador de Contribuciones directas; inability to collect taxes.
  - 3884 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Cuernavaca, February 26, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for interview in Toluca; travel to Tepalcingo; Subprefecto de Tetecala; growing opposition of Indians at Puente de Ixtla and Tepalcingo to payment of the capitación; plan for uprising at the romería; Arellano suspected to be at Chalcacingo (?); travel to Tepaltzingo explained as road inspection; aid from troops at Morelos and Jonacatepec and from cavalry of General P. Palacios.
  - 3885 Acosta, Benito León. Chalco, February 26, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Plans for opening canal for navigation; request for permit; transmittal of legal papers; address in Mexico in care of Diego Merino.
  - 3886 Rovalo, Luis. Mexico, February 27, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request, supported by Arróyabe, that Teniente retirado Oliveros and Juan Ruiz of the rurales be placed under the jurisdiction of the Comandante general; continued bandit problem; controls by the Comandante militar and the Juez de Chalco.
  - 3887 Escudero, P[edro]. Mexico, February 27, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Efforts of Rovalo to increase brandy production in Morelos; ill feeling between Oliveros and Sierra; news from Álvarez about Varela requested; legislative action on the Luz litigation recommended.
  - 3888 Riva Palacio, Mariano. [Borrador de carta a Anselmo Zurutuza.] Toluca, February 28, 1850. Unsigned., 1 l. 15 × 21 cm.
    Petition to Congress on toll payment on local road; Becerril; delay in stopping repairs on Cuernavaca road.
  - 3889 Vargas, Jesús María. Yahualica, February 28, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Tax collection in Sochicoayan (?).
  - 3890 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, February 28, 1850. LS. 2 l. 21 × 26 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Transmittal of Memoria read to the Congreso de la Unión.
  - 3891 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Mexico, February 28, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Problems in collecting the capitación; warning from Texcoco; military aid promised by the Ministro de la Guerra; Subprefecto de Teotihuacán; guards at Venta de Córdoba and at Tlalmanalco and Ozumba; aid from Ameca; loan by the Marqués de Salinas.
  - 3891A Álvarez, J[uan]. Iguala, March 1, 18[50]. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead: Correspondencia particular del Comandante General del Estado Libre y Soberano de Guerrero.
    Aid requested for Lic. Agustín P. Gavilán in claim for back pay as Juez de Acapulco. Last use of this type of letterhead. It was first used [this collection] in November, 1849.
  - 3892 Alcocer, Luis A. San Pablo, March 1, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Contributions to the penitenciaría fund by Villaseñor and Caballero; supply of lime; transportation taken by bandits.
  - 3893 DIRECCIÓN GENERAL DE ADUANAS MARÍTIMAS FRONTERIZAS Y RENTAS NO ESTANCADAS. Mexico, March 2, 1850. ALS. Signed: Ignacio Sierra y Rosso. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Testamentaría de Ignacio Moya; resignation of albacea; Atristain; appointment of Miguel Irisarri; alcabala for sale of Hacienda de Tetelco; Juez Madrid; instructions to Administrador Herrera requested; need for end of litigation.
  - 3894 Arévalo, Manuel M. Ixmiquilpan, March 2, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Illness of wife; approval of Ley de capitación.
  - 3895 García, Fernando. Cuernavaca, March 3, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Authorship of verses in Toluca newspaper denied; Rodin(?); blame laid on personal enemies.
  - 3896 Yáñez, José Y. Cuernavaca, May 3, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Decreased revenues from brandy production; enforcement of the Ley de capitación; difficulty in forming the padrones.
  - 3897 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, March 3, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Unrest in Otzoloapam; meeting with the Prefecto; Junta calificadora; Ley de reemplazos in the Municipalidades foráneas; collection of the capitación; tax; Temascaltepec; Villa del Valle.
  - 3898 Sánchez, Atilano. Mexico, March 3, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Request for intervention with the Juez de Ixtlahuaca to hasten settlement of change of title in the case of the sale of Hacienda de Enyege to Bishop Joaquín Fernández Madrid and brothers; payment of the alcabala.
  - 3899 Riva Palacio, Mariano. [Borrador de carta a Felipe Neri del Barrio.] Toluca, March 4, 1850. Unsigned., 4 l. 15 × 21 cm.
    Problem of the alcabala to be paid on Rancho de Atla; forced loan in Law of April 22, 1847 resisted by Señora Pavón and husband on grounds of not being Mexicans; claim allowed by Administrador de Teotihuacán; Escribano Madariaga; question of ownership; Bascón presumed owner; payments to Señora Fagoaga.
  - 3900 Alas, M[anuel]. Arcos, March 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for establishment of assay office; Zamudio; Calderón.
  - 3901 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, March 4, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Transmittal of copy of his Memoria to governors and to Comandantes generales.
  - 3902 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Mexico, March 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Report from Teotihuacán of armed band at Cerro de Texquiquac; Arista's aid; low revenues in Texcoco; Marqués de Salinas; need for horses; funds requested from Chalco or Teotihuacán; troops from Córdoba and Tlalmanalco to aid Juez de Chalco at Hacienda de Zoquiapa.
  - 3903 Espejo, José B. Morelos, March 4, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of voluminous legal papers from Jonacatepec; delay in forwarding them; problem of organizing the padrones for the capitación; García Salas to be sent to Jonacatepec.
  - 3904 Rivero, Nasario. Tlalpam, March 4, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Problem of establishing the capitation tax; illness.
  - 3905 Sein, A. Tula, March 4, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Letter sent to Ildefonso Tapia in Mixquiahuala; Leocadio Tapia; difficulty of establishing the capitation tax and the padrón; fine of defaulters.
  - 3906 Riva Palacio, Mariano. [Borrador de carta a Luis Rovalo.] Toluca, March 5, 1850. Unsigned. 1 l. 21 × 26 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Financial condition of the treasury at beginning of his term; need for loan; Escudero; Cuautla.
  - 3907 Cano, Anselmo. Mexico, March 5, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 15 × 21 cm.
    Illness of Quintana Roo; letters for Herrera and Arista; Villar; promise of military aid by Arista; promise of Dr. Barrientos to reprimand Cura Mendoza for opposing justice and inciting Indians.
  - 3908 Escudero, P[edro]. Mexico, March 5, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    The Luz litigation; gift of paper and cigars; San Agustín; gambling preparations in Tacubaya; permit for judges of Sultepec and Pachuca; Romero; Aguirre.
  - 3909 García de la Mora, Ignacio. Chihuahua, March 5, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Aid requested in obtaining post in Casa de Moneda; Ángel Frías; Lolita.
  - 3910 Herrera, José J. de. Mexico, March 5, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Armed aid sent by Arista to Juez de Letras de Apan; military support promised.
  - 3911 Álvarez, Juan. Iguala, March 5, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Petition of citizens of Mazatepec for erection of a new municipalidad with it as head.
  - 3912 Colín, José Nicolás E. de. Asunción, March 5, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Letters for Luis Colín, Garrido, and Velázquez; Cura de Ameca; complaint of Juez de Letras de Chalco to the Alcalde on theft of water; reconnaissance with Santos and interview with Gabino Martínez; pipe project; el Cerro; Temamatla; stone for stonemasons carried by mule; plowing in Tejocote, Gavillero, and Chilar, and Tlecanextlale; payroll money borrowed from El Moral; corn sold in Chalco; Cadena.
  - 3913 Álvarez, Juan. Iguala, March 5, 1850. LS., 3 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Promise of employment for Lic. Trinidad Gómez; removal of capital to Ciudad Guerrero. Includes draft of answer, Toluca, March 15, 1850, recommending Gómez and urging caution in governing the new state.
  - 3914 Goribar, J. de. Mexico, March 6, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recovery from illness; receipt from Melchor Carrasco for contribution to the prison construction.
  - 3915 Malo, José R. Mexico, March 6, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Hope for legislative action (on Luz litigation); Escudero; Ocampo appointed Ministro de Hacienda; cholera in Michoacán.
  - 3916 Silva, Ignacio. Cuernavaca, March 6, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.